Guide to the Pucketos Garden Club Records, 1929-2014 AIS.2014.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pucketos Garden Club Records
1930s-2000s
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pucketos Garden Club (New Kensington, Pa.)
AIS.2014.02
2.5 Linear Feet (3 boxes, 8 scrapbooks and 10 photo albums)
This collection is comprised of materials from the Pucketos Garden Club of New Kensington, Pa.. It contains manuscript materials, photographs, and scrapbooks documenting the activities of the club.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into seven series ranging from the 1930s to 2014. Additional information about each series is included in the scope and content notes within each series.
Series I. Flower Shows
Series II. Awards
Series III. People Against Litter
Series IV. General Records
Series V. Yearbooks
Series VI. Scrapbooks
Series VII. Photographs
Scope and Content Notes
The Pucketos Garden Club Records contains primarily materials created by the garden club between the 1930s and 2000s. It contains seven series including flower show materials, awards, newspaper clippings, committee meeting minutes, club communications, yearbooks, and material related to People Against Litter, an environmentalist group created by the Pucketos. In addition, the collection contains photographs, albums, and yearbooks.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
Pucketos Garden Club Records, 1929-2014, AIS.2014.02, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
History
The Pucketos (Poe-key-tos) Garden Club was created in 1933 in New Kensington, Pa., at the suggestion of T.H. Hurt, the president of a men's garden club that was disbanding. Forty women attended the first meeting on September 14, 1933 and elected Mrs. H. Burns Smith as the first president. The club adopted its bylaws and constitution on October 2, 1933. Membership ranged from 80 women to around 60 today.
The name "Pucketos" developed as a tribute to their local history. It comes from Puckety Creek, which enters the Allegheny River, and the Pucketa Indian Trial, which runs from Export, Pa., to present day New Kensington. The activities of the club are outlined in their constitution: "to encourage the planting of gardens, to study methods of plant cultivation, to stimulate interest in cooperative gardening, to aid in the protection of wild flowers and birds, to cooperate in neighborhood betterment." Specifically, the club members participated in field trips to different gardens around Pittsburgh and the surrounding area, flower shows presented by the Pucketos and other local garden clubs, state competitions, and planting projects throughout the New Kensington area.
During the second half of the twentieth century, the club placed an increase focus on environmental protection. In 1986, Ruth Barkley, the club's Litter Awareness Chair, created the People Against Litter program that was active through the 1990s. The focus on environmentalism continues today as multiple committees report on environmental concerns.
The Pucketos documented their activities primarily through scrapbooks of photographs and newspaper clippings, as well as yearbooks and administrative papers.
Related Material
Garden Club of Allegheny County Records, 1913-2012, AIS.2006.07, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Fox Chapel Garden Club Records, AIS.2011.10, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Garden Club of Forest Hills Records, 1923-2011, AIS.2013.07, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Historic Landscape Survey of Allegheny County Records, 1970-2002, AIS.2005.01, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Societies -- Pennsylvania; Societies; Gardening -- Societies, etc; Gardening -- Pennsylvania -- New Kensington -- Societies, etc; Gardening -- Pennsylvania -- Westmoreland County -- Societies, etc.; Environmental protection -- Pennsylvania -- Westmoreland County; New Kensington (Pa.); Westmoreland County (Pa.); Minutes (Administrative records); Clippings (Information artifacts); Photographs; Scrapbooks; Albums; Yearbooks; Women; Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania; Pucketos Garden Club (New Kensington, Pa.)
- Flower Shows, 1944-2009; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains flower show materials from both the Pucketos Garden Club and other garden clubs from the Pittsburgh area. Arranged alphabetically by garden club, with miscellaneous materials at the end.
  - Ayr Hill, Bear Creek Fork, Stonewall, and Manor Garden Clubs, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Burreuton Garden Club, 1964-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Churchill & Ridgewood Manor Garden Clubs, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Fox Chapel Garden Club, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania, 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Garden Club of Munhall, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Glenview Garden, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Murrysville Garden Club, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Requirements for National Council Standard, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Oakmont, Dark Hollow, Spade and Trowel, and Men's Garden Clubs, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Penn Hebron Garden Club, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Philadelphia International Flower Show, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Pittsburgh Garden Center, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Pucketos Garden Club, 1940s, 1944, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Pucketos Garden Club, 1950s, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Pucketos Garden Club, 1960s, 1962-1969 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Pucketos Garden Club, 1970s, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Pucketos Garden Club, 1980s, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Pucketos Garden Club, "The Madonna Story", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Pucketos Garden Club, Expenses, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Pucketos Garden Club, Flower Show Floorplan, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Westmoreland Garden Club, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Women's Committee, "Art in Bloom", 2009 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Flower and Design Instructional Materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Classification Committee, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "From the Judging Viewpoint", Circa late 1970s (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Awards, 1929-2007; II.
  Series II contains award applications and awards given to the Pucketos Garden Club for a variety of competitions and special recognition, spanning the length of the club's existence.
  - Alle-Kiski Area HOPE Center, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Dr. Glen Long for prize roses, 1929-1931 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Garden Club Federation of Pennyslvania, 1960s, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania, Award Rules and Applications, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Garden Club Federation of Pennyslvania, 1980s, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania, 2000s, 2000-2007 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Habitat for Humanity, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - National Council of Garden Clubs, Mrs. Stewart re: award application, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - National Council of Garden Clubs, Flower Show Achievement Award [framed ribbon], 1976 (Box 1, Frame 1)
  - National Council of State Garden Clubs, Inc., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - National Garden Clubs, Inc., 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - National Wildlife Federation, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1972-1997 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Pucketos Garden Club, "My Plant", undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - State Award Application, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - State Award Application, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Meetings, 1949-2010; III.
  This series includes minutes for three club committees, meeting programs and fliers, and event fliers. Arranged chronologically.
  - Committee Meetings, 1998-2010; 1.
    Subseries I contains meeting minutes for three Pucketos Garden Club Committees: the Twenty-fifth Anniversary Committee, Executive Board, and General Membership Meeting. Arranged by committee and chronologically.
    - Twenty-fifth Anniversary, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Twenty-fifth Anniversary, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Executive Board, 2008-2010 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - General Business Meetings, 2008-2010 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1949-2010; 2.
    This subseries contains general meeting notices, miscellaneous meeting information, and newspaper clippings regarding Club meetings. It is arranged by subject and chronologically.
    - Meeting Notices, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Meeting Notices, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Meeting Notices, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Meeting Notices, 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Meeting Program, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Annual Business Meeting Agenda, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - "Garden Club Notes and Reminders", 1989 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - The Pucketos Petaler, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Monthly Plans, undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Pucketos Garden Club Invitations, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1983-1989 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Newspaper Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1970-2010 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - General Membership Events, 1947-2010; 3.
    Subseries III contains promotional material and newspaper articles regarding Pucketos Garden Club events. It is arranged chronologically and by document type.
    - Golden Anniversary Program, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Event Flyers, 2007-2010 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - "It's a Calendar Tea", undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - "Table Talk", undated (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Civic Dept. Conservation Garden Therapy Youth Activities Bookmarks, undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Newspaper Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 71)
- People Against Litter, 1986-1989; IV.
  People Against Litter was an environmental organization created by the Pucketos Garden Club in the 1980s. This series includes newspaper and magazine articles, environmental materials, and a scrapbook.
  - Scrapbook, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 72-74)
  - Article in Keystone Gardener, Spring 1987 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Pittsburgh Trash and Recycling, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Environmental Shopper's Pledge, undated (Box 1, Folder 78)
- General Records, 1943-2010; V.
  This series includes miscellaneous documents, such as correspondence, garden materials, and Pucketos historical documents. Arranged by relation to the Pucketos Garden Club and then chronologically.
  - Constitution, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - "The Heart of Your Community" Radio Broadcast Transcripts, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Officers and Committee Chairpersons, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - "Celebrating 75! A to Z" Booklet, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Pucketos Notecards (blank), undated (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Correspondence, 1949-2010 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Notes, 1979-2006 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - "Good and Bad News from the Birdworld" Article, undated (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Gardening and Flower Materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Pittsburgh Garden Center News Bulletin, 1950-1970 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Garden Club Federation of Pennyslvania, Keystone Gardener, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Garden Club Federation of Pennyslvania, Membership Materials, 2007-2010 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - State Convention Applicaton, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - College Club of Pittsburgh Booklet, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 92)
- Yearbooks, 1937-2012; VI.
  This series includes the Pucketos Garden Club's yearbooks from 1937-2012. Arranged chronologically.
  - Yearbooks, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Yearbooks, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Yearbooks, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Yearbooks, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Yearbooks, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Yearbooks, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Yearbooks, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Yearbooks, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Yearbooks, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Yearbooks, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Yearbooks, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - Yearbooks, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - Yearbooks, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - Yearbooks, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - Yearbooks, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - Yearbooks, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - Yearbooks, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Yearbooks, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Yearbooks, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Yearbooks, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Yearbooks, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Yearbooks, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Yearbooks, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Yearbooks, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Yearbooks, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Yearbooks, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Yearbooks, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Yearbooks, 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Yearbooks, 2008-2009 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Yearbooks, 2010-2011 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Yearbooks, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Evening Department Yearbooks, c1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Scrapbooks, 1930s-2000s; VII.
  This series is comprised of approximately 10 scrapbooks complied by various members of the club, with dates ranging from the 1930s-2000s. Some are in folders and some are wrapped. Arranged by location and chronologically.
  - Scrapbooks, 1950-1979 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Scrapbook complied by Edna Mae Kreistlite, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbooks, 1934-1939 (Shelf 1, Volume 1)
  - Scrapbooks, 1936-1947 (Shelf 1, Volume 2)
  - Scrapbooks, 1940-1950 (Shelf 1, Volume 3)
  - Scrapbooks, 1951-1961 (Shelf 1, Volume 4)
  - Scrapbooks, 1962-1966 (Shelf 1, Volume 5)
  - Scrapbooks, 1972-1978 (Shelf 1, Volume 6)
  - Scrapbooks, 1985-1986 (Shelf 1, Volume 7)
  - Scrapbooks, 1986-1988 (Shelf 1, Volume 8)
- Photographs, 1963-2014; VIII.
  This series contains loose photographs spanning from the 1950s-2010s and 10 photograph albums. The images are of Pucketos events, gardens, and members. The series is arranged chronologically and by location.
  - Valley Daily News, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Event, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Mrs. Bailey's Rose Garden, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Color Copies/Digital Prints of Gardens, ca. 1970 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Garden Show Event, ca. 1970s (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Golden Anniversary, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - December Events, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - October Events, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - December Events, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - July Event, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Events, ca. 1991 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Pennsylvania State Convention, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Arbor Day Tree Planting in Memorial Park, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - 75th Anniversary Event, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Flower Baskets Event, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Valentine's Day Garden Therapy Project, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - March Events, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Crooked Creek Event, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Niagara Trip, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Erie Bus Trip, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - "Shadowwood Int." Event, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - November Event, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Christmas Meeting, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Philadelphia Flower Show, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Art in Bloom, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Flower Garden, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Tree Planting Ceremony, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - February Event, c2010 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - May Youth Activities Album, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Summer Activities and Field Trips, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Pucketos Gardens Album, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Longwood and Winterthur Field Trip Albums, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Christmas Trees, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Flower Show, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Sport Days Event, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Tea Event, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Group Photograph at Penn State New Kensington Nature Trail, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Greensburg Garden Center, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Arbor Day Event, undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Unknown, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Album, 1990-1991 (Shelf 1, Volume 9)
  - Album, 1993-1995 (Shelf 1, Volume 10)
  - Album, 1996-1998 (Shelf 1, Volume 11)
  - Album, 1999 (Shelf 1, Volume 12)
  - Album, 2002 (Shelf 1, Volume 13)
  - Album, 2004-2005 (Shelf 1, Volume 14)
  - Album, 2006 (Shelf 1, Volume 15)
  - Album, 2007 (Shelf 1, Volume 16)
  - Album, 2008 (Shelf 1, Volume 17)
  - Album, 2012 (Shelf 1, Volume 18)